Guide to the Woolmer Collection of Cormac McCarthy
The Wittliff Collections
Woolmer Collection of Cormac McCarthy
1969-2006
The Wittliff Collections
McCarthy, Cormac, 1933-; Woolmer, J. Howard
SWWC.092
2.5 Linear Feet
5 boxes
The Woolmer Collection of Cormac McCarthy spans 1969-2006 and documents the professional and personal friendship between the book collector and McCarthy. The collection is arranged in four series: Correspondence, Writings by McCarthy, Writings about McCarthy, and Woolmer's Bibliography Files.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchase, 2006
Biographical Notes
Book collector and bibliographer, J. Howard Woolmer, wrote to Cormac McCarthy praising both Outer Dark (1968) and McCarthy's first novel, The Orchard Keeper (1965) after reading Robert Coles' review of Outer Dark published in the March 22, 1969 issue of The New Yorker. In his July 29, 1969 letter, Woolmer states his intent to begin collecting all of McCarthy's work and asks if the author would be willing to sign copies of his books. In his August 16 reply, McCarthy agrees. These letters mark the first of over 120 sent between the two men from 1969 to 2006.
By 1969, Woolmer had been in the book selling business for almost ten years. Operating out of the literary Mecca of New York City, he issued his first catalogue in 1961. His early catalogues were of modern first editions and on the works of literary giants such as James Joyce. Woolmer soon began issuing catalogues based on single subjects; the first on the Imagist Poets (1966) and then, in 1969, on the novelist Malcolm Lowry, author of Under the Volcano. He has since published a bibliography on Malcolm Lowry; A Checklist of the Hogarth Press; and a bibliography of the Leonard L. Milberg Irish Theatre Collection.
In a 2007 interview, Woolmer stated that he had initially moved away from modern firsts because "I didn't get enough of a kick from the books of contemporary writers." However, with Cormac McCarthy he had discovered an exception, and over the next thirty years he amassed a remarkable collection of signed first editions, advance proofs, and foreign imprints of McCarthy's books. The Wittliff Collections purchased these books in 2006 along with the collection of letters between McCarthy and Woolmer.
Related Materials
Books in the Woolmer Collection have been cataloged and the records are searchable through the Alkek Library online catalog, http://catalog.library.txstate.edu
Scope and Contents
The Woolmer Collection of Cormac McCarthy spans 1969-2006 and documents the professional and personal friendship between the book collector and McCarthy. The collection is arranged in four series: Correspondence, Writings by McCarthy, Writings about McCarthy, and Woolmer's Bibliography Files.
Series I: Correspondence, 1996-2006 (box 1), contains 120 letters between McCarthy and Woolmer. The letters are arranged chronologically. The majority of the letters discuss McCarthy's writing, but other topics include recommendations of books to read, reviews of McCarthy's work, and the book collecting world. More detailed descriptions of each letter are found in the container list beginning on page 5.
Series II: Writings by McCarthy, 1982-1994 (boxes 1-4), includes photocopies of drafts of Blood Meridian, The Crossing, Cities of the Plain, The Road, The Stonemason, and The Gardener's Son. The works are arranged into following subseries: Novels, Plays, and Screenplays.
Series III: Writings about McCarthy, 1974-2006 (boxes 4-5), comprises reviews and articles about McCarthy from Esquire, The New Yorker, Southern Literary Journal, Texas Monthly, and other publications. The writings are arranged alphabetically by author. Also included are a number off clippings files about McCarthy and a small collection of ephemera such as publishers catalogs, flyers, and press packets.
Series IV: J. Howard Woolmer bibliography files, 1986-2006, (box 5), consists of Woolmer's files and notes on a possible bibliography on McCarthy. Of note are Woolmer's correspondence files regarding collecting McCarthy.
Related Materials
The Wittliff Collections also holds the Cormac McCarthy Papers, materials related to the production of Perspectives on Cormac McCarthy and John Sepich's Notes on Blood Meridian, as well as a small collection of Cormac McCarthy screenplays donated by McCarthy and Bill and Sally Wittliff.
Authors, American; Book collecting -- United States; Correspondence; Woolmer, J. Howard; McCarthy, Cormac, 1933-
- Correspondence, 1969-2006
  Series Description
  Correspondence contains 120 letters between McCarthy and Woolmer. The letters are arranged chronologically. The majority of the letters discuss McCarthy's writing, but other topics include recommendations of books to read, reviews of McCarthy's work, and the book collecting world.
  - Woolmer to McCarthy. Carbon, 1 page, July 29, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Contents
    Praising Outer Dark and asking if McCarthy will inscribe books.
  - McCarthy to Woolmer. TLS, 1 p, with a holograph addition, August 16, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    "Thank you for your very kind letter…" Mentions stories in Yale Review and Sewanee Review. "I don't write short stories…I won't have another book finished for a couple of years." He will inscribe the books.
  - Woolmer to McCarthy. Carbon, 1 page, August 20, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Asking about foreign editions, and promising a complimentary subscription to Works, a magazine that Woolmer had a hand in publishing.
  - Woolmer to McCarthy. Carbon, 1 page, September 9, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Thanking for inscribed books.
  - McCarthy to Woolmer. TLS, 1 page, February 17, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    "Thank you for the letter and note…I have an artist friend who wants to do an illustrated edition of my forthcoming book [Child of God] but it remains to be seen whether the publisher will take to the idea." Supplies the names of publishers of foreign editions of his books. Thanks Woolmer for Works: "I was really amazed at the quality of material they're publishing. Most literary quarterlies these days are pretty grim. I particularly liked Lyn Lifshin's poems. And Paul Blackburn's Bertran de Born."
  - McCarthy to Woolmer. TLS, 1 page, January 21, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    "Thank you for the book of poems…This girl is very good. I particularly liked 'You who rejoice in Symmetry', but of the ones I have had a chance to read there are none bad…"
  - Woolmer to McCarthy. Carbon, 1 page, April 28, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Inquiring about purchasing manuscripts, corrected galleys, etc. of The Orchard Keeper and Outer Dark.
  - McCarthy to Woolmer. TLS, 1 page, June 28, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    "Sorry to be so long in answering your letter. The new book [Child of God] is on the fall lists and will be out, I am told, in December. It is not the longer book that I was writing, but a shorter one which intruded itself in the middle of writing the other one." Replies to Woolmer's inquiry about buying manuscripts saying he has all the "stuff" and would consider an offer if Woolmer tendered one.
  - Woolmer to McCarthy. Carbon, 1 page, July 23, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Asking for an inventory of manuscripts in order to make an offer.
  - Woolmer to McCarthy. Carbon, 1 page, January 22, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Praising Child of God. Includes duplicates of newspaper clippings enclosed with the letter.
  - McCarthy to Woolmer. TLS, 1 page, March 12, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    "Thanks for you letter and the comments on the book…" Sends new address in Tucson and agrees to sign books. Hasn't had a chance to go through his manuscripts.
  - Woolmer to McCarthy. Carbon, 1 page, March 15, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Sending Child of God for signature. Mentions the possibility of McCarthy's papers going to a university library.
  - Woolmer to McCarthy. Carbon, 1 page, November 15, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Mentioning PBS advertisement in NY Times for The Gardeners Son. Requests a copy of the script. [Copy of NY Times ad included.]
  - McCarthy to Woolmer, ALS, 2 pages, December 13, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    "Thanks for your letter. Sorry you've been looking for my book without success…" Is going to have a copy of the typescript of The Gardner's Son made for Woolmer and would like a copy of The Michael Fraenkel - Henry Miller Correspondence, Called Hamlet in return.
  - Woolmer to McCarthy. Carbon, 1 page, January 7, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Sending the Miller-Fraenkel book; discussing the reviews of The Gardener's Son; and asking about early works in preparation for a possible bibliography [as yet unpublished]. Corresponding New York Times advertisement for the PBS Visions series, and a November / December 1976 issue of Coda: Poets and Writers Newsletter with mention of the series on p. 9.
  - McCarthy to Woolmer. ALS, 1 page, January 26, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    "Thank you for the book. It is very exotic looking. This was the only one of Millers books I didnt have and I've been looking forward to reading it for years…" Mentions his early publications: "I'm afraid theres not much research to do in the way of bibliography. Think I published a story once in a college rag…When I started writing novels I stopped writing anything else. Never wrote no poetry." Ends with "I'm in Tucson working on my 'western' [Blood Meridian] Long book supposed to be out this year but maybe not."
  - Woolmer to McCarthy. Carbon, 1 page, January 9, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Thanking him for typescript and asking to have it signed. Suggests Woolmer/Brotherson publish a limited signed edition of "Burial" [previously published in Antaeus].
  - McCarthy to Woolmer. ALS, 1 page, February 2, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    "Thank you for the note. Letter, I guess…" Mentions he did not know that Antaeus had published an excerpt from Suttree. "I dont like to find my name in little magazines, but the idea of a limited edition sounds interesting. I'm working on a western [Blood Meridian] – based loosely on historical events in Mexico in 1849 – illustrated with about 2 dozen period prints – woodcuts mostly. The book is essentially finished (300 pp) but needs to be completely rewritten…"
  - Woolmer to McCarthy. Carbon, 1 page, March 10, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Regarding Suttree, which he does not like as much as McCarthy's other works, but feels it is still "miles ahead of anything being written by any other writer." Asks if McCarthy uses a typewriter; discusses possibility of publishing McCarthy's "western."
  - McCarthy to Woolmer. No envelope. ALS, 1 page, undated, circa 1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    "Thank you for your letter and here's your book…" Robert Coles sent him proofs of a review to appear in the New Yorker. Mentions another review: "I suppose by now you may have seen the thing in Esquire, I enjoyed the cartoon. Thought it showed a wit and discernment the reviewer [Geoffrey Wolff] could have used. Also the cartoonist managed to get all the words spelled right." Answers Woolmer's question about his writing process: "I normally use a typewriter (you asked) and I think you can see why." Mentions that Random House has publishing rights for "the western" but that maybe Woolmer can publish an excerpt.
  - Woolmer to McCarthy, Carbon, 1 page, May 18, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Providing details of publishing history.
  - McCarthy to Woolmer. ALS, 1 pages, May 1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    "Thank you very much for the Levertov. It is very handsome…" mentions Kosinki's book in passing, agrees that Esquire has fallen on hard times, he's seen a number of reviews, some of them nice ones. Mentions that his editor is Albert Erskine and that Woolmer should contact him about publishing the excerpt.
  - Woolmer to McCarthy Carbon, 1 page, June 22, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Regarding publishing an excerpt of Blood Meridian.
  - McCarthy to Woolmer. ALS, 1 page, October 16, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    "What are you doing? Did you ever hear from Albert about the limited signed edition…?"
  - Woolmer to McCarthy. Carbon, 1 page, October 31, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Regarding cancelled trip to Vanderbilt and response received from Albert Erskine.
  - McCarthy to Woolmer. TLS, 1 page, November 5, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    "Sorry you didnt get down to Nashville, would have enjoyed seeing you…" Discusses Random House, "Albert is semi-retired and probably considered some sort of relic of bygone years by the functional illiterates now in command…" Also, "a short section of the western is to appear – I am told – in the next issue of Triquarterly. The issue being devoted to the literature of the West. I'm branching out."
  - Woolmer to McCarthy. Carbon, 1 page, March 5, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Informing him that Robert Penn Warren considers McCarthy a "most talented writer." Recommends the film Wise Blood.
  - McCarthy to Woolmer. TLS, 1 page, April 1, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    "Thank you for your very nice letter…" Mentions that Robert Penn Warren and he share the same editor at Random House [Erskine]. "Interesting that he [Warren] liked Child of God. Some people think it a most peculiar book, but lately it has been receiving a sort of belated enthusiasm in the form of reviews and theses and such." Mentions that Wise Blood actors Brad Dourif and Ned Beatty were also both in The Gardner's Son.
  - Woolmer to McCarthy. Carbon, 1 page, May 19, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Sending May 2, 1980 TLS review of Suttree [review included].
  - McCarthy to Woolmer. ALS, 2 pages, August 12, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    "Thanks for the clipping. You were right, I probably would not have seen it…I'm getting ready to head west for the final push on my novel [Blood Meridian]. Hope to get it done by the end of the year." Erskine and Random House are very negative about a limited edition. "I don't have an agent anymore and am in a sort of limbo…" All of his books except for the most recent are out of print; inquires if Woolmer knows of a paperback house that might be interested.
  - Woolmer to McCarthy. Carbon, 1 page, December 18, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Received Triquarterly. "The Scalphunters" is powerful, but confused about characters. Comments on the stuffing genitals into victim's mouths. Mentions reading John Yount.
  - McCarthy to Woolmer. ALS, 2 pages, January 27, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    "Thanks for your letter, it is always nice to hear from you…The characters in the story [Blood Meridian] are a bunch of American adventurers in Chihuahua in 1849 who have contracted to supply scalps to the government…" Mentions John Yount's The Trapper's Last Shot. Also mentions getting "a little windfall from a foundation [MacArthur] so expect to stay in business a while longer." Might go to Europe.
  - Woolmer to McCarthy. Carbon, 1 page, February 23, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Suggests getting together if McCarthy comes out East.
  - McCarthy to Woolmer. ALS, 4 pages (1 sheet folded in half), June 22, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    "I'm looking for a book for a friend of mine and thought maybe you could help me…" Forty-Four Years of the Life of a Hunter by Meschach [sic] Browning. "The western proceeds apace – not a blistering pace, I suppose, but it goes." Describes getting caught in the middle of a gunfight between police and criminals in Knoxville, "A news lady rushed up to me with a microphone and a tape recorder and asked me what was going on. I told her I had no idea, but it certainly seemed like the good old days for a few minutes."
  - Woolmer to McCarthy. Carbon, 1 page, July 3, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Promising to look for the Browning book. Asks if McCarthy couldn't use a good agent.
  - McCarthy to Woolmer. ALS, 4 pages (1 sheet folded in half), July 15, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    "Thanks for the letter. Yes, the Meschach [sic] Browning book is what I need…" States his literary affairs are "a long and tiresome tale at best…. My agent for several years was Candida Donadio...she expressed her satisfaction at representing me personally and negotiated the contract for the book with which I am now occupied. That was the last I ever heard of her…I wrote and told her I'd like to make official what already existed in fact and we amicably parted…After this I wrote some other agents who'd been recommended to me by a friend but the one or two who wrote back seemed less than jubilant about the prospects of representing me. So Random House is now my agent…"
  - Woolmer to McCarthy. Carbon, 1 page, October 6, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Has asked John Malcolm Brinnin [Gertrude Stein and Dylan Thomas biographer] about agents and his is Dorothy Olding of the Harold Ober Associates, Inc. Waiting for "the western" to come out; is buying up copies of Orchard Keeper to hand out to friends.
  - McCarthy to Woolmer. ALS, 1 page, October 28, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    "Good to hear from you. Thank you for your inquiries on my behalf…" Planning a trip to New York at beginning of new year. Random House has sold the paperback rights to his early books to the Ecco Press.
  - Woolmer to McCarthy. Carbon, 1 page, November 23, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Congratulations on receiving the MacArthur grant. Wall Street Journal clipping about the grant from November 19, 1981 included.
  - McCarthy to Woolmer. ALS, 1 page, December 9, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    "Thank you for the letter and the good wishes…The MacArthur people just call you up and ask where to send the checks. It was something of a shock...My creditors seem much gratified…I am still struggling with my mss, but it goes ok…"
  - Woolmer to McCarthy. Carbon, 1 page, May 4, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Recommending agent Peter Shepherd who handles Muriel Spark in the U.S. and suggests McCarthy contact him.
  - McCarthy to Woolmer. ALS, 1 page, May 24, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    "Thanks for the letter. Please dont apologize for trying to find readers for my books…In the same mail came a letter from Peter Shepherd asking that I call him – which I've done…"
  - Woolmer to McCarthy. Carbon, 1 page, May 28, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Gave copy of Orchard Keeper to neighbor who is reading it for a second time. Sending photo for inscription.
  - McCarthy to Woolmer. ALS on Hausman's laundry ticket, NYC, circa 1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    "Here's your photo…" [Photo not included].
  - Woolmer to McCarthy. Carbon, 1 page, June 20, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Thanks for signing the photograph.
  - Woolmer to Albert Erskine, Jr. Carbon, 1 page, June 25, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Asking for publication information on all of the printings of McCarthy's books.
  - Lane, Sharon [Random House] to Woolmer. TLS, 1 page, July 25, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Sending some publication information on McCarthy books.
  - Woolmer to McCarthy. Carbon, 1 page, November 29, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Asking when western will be published; inquires about status of agent search
  - McCarthy to Woolmer. ALS, 1 page, December 10, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    "Thanks for your letter, 'twas good to hear from you… the western - entitled Blood Meridian or The Evening of Redness In the West is set and proofread and will appear – I am told – in March…" More about his search for an agent; Ecco Press has brought out his early books.
  - Woolmer to McCarthy. Carbon, 1 page, December 16, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Glad Blood Meridian is coming out; offers $100 to buy Xerox copy McCarthy had sent to Peter Shepherd [copy in box 1 folders 10 and 11].
  - Woolmer to McCarthy. Carbon, 1 page, February 1, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Received the Xerox copy from Peter Shepherd; surprised at Shepherd's lack of response to McCarthy. Praises Blood Meridian; asks if McCarthy actually traveled the country described. Endorsed/canceled check to McCarthy included, as is a Spring 1985 advertisement for Random House.
  - McCarthy to Woolmer. ALS, 1 page (no envelope), circa 1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    "Glad that you got the Xerox…" and refunds $50.00. "To answer your question, I spent several years in the country described. I've taken the train to Mochos a couple of times and it is a great trip…"
  - Woolmer to McCarthy. Carbon, 1 page, February 16, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Received his copy of Blood Meridian; likes the Dali painting. Will send copy for inscription if McCarthy agrees.
  - McCarthy to Woolmer. ALS, 1 page, March 12, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    "By all means send the book and I will be happy to scribble in it and return it…Saw a nice review in USA Today (national newspaper) this past week-end but nothing other. Book in a few stores friends tell me…"
  - Woolmer to McCarthy. Carbon, 1 page, March 18, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Sending copy of Blood Meridian for signature; discusses reviews and mentions meeting Dali once.
  - Woolmer to McCarthy. Carbon, 1 page, May 2, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Sending Xerox of Times review. Mentions meeting Albert Erskine at a fugitive poets exhibit at The University of Virginia. Newspaper clipping from April 28, 1985 Times included.
  - McCarthy to Woolmer. ALS, 2 pages, June 28, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    "Thank you very much for sending the Southern Literary Journal. Discusses Erskine. "Mostly these days I'm trying to get a film script produced into a film. The MacArthur largess expires in a little over a year and I've gotten used to eating regularly and dont know what will happen when the money stops. Other than that I have 2 or 3 novels that I have notes and a few sections for but I dont know which one to hone in on. Probably the most difficult one…"
  - McCarthy to Woolmer. ALS, 1 page, October 16, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    "Thanks for sending the review (Images of the Southern Writer)…" Just back from a week-long rafting/hiking trip in Big Bend. "I'm working on a couple of stories in filmscript form. Very good form for conserving the word…"
  - McCarthy to Woolmer. ALS, 1 page, November 4, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    "My good friend and attorney here - Bobby Perel - has an opportunity to buy an original set of Curtis's Indian photographs…" Asks if Woolmer knows what they might be worth. McCarthy's brother and wife visited and they went rafting down the Rio Grande "Very beautiful country. It rained in the night and the river came up 5 feet and we brought out refugees with us…"
  - Woolmer to McCarthy. Photocopy with holograph addition, 1 page, November 20, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Curtis' The North American Indian valued at about $50,000. Advises about what attorney should look for; offers to help auction it.
  - Woolmer to McCarthy. Carbon, 1 page, November 23, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Follow-up on Curtis book. Recent auction at only $22,000 but not a fine set.
  - Woolmer to McCarthy. Carbon, 1 page, December 17, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Christmas greetings.
  - McCarthy to Woolmer. ALS, 2 pages, December 17, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    "Ecco sent me about a half dozen of these [advance cover for paperback Blood Meridian] and I was just [martialing] all forces for a note to you I should I would send you one…" The Curtis book "has escaped." Asks what book Woolmer is working on. Included: advance cover inscribed "Guaranteed to be the first autographed copy. All the best, Cormac."
  - Woolmer to McCarthy. Photocopy, 1 page, December 24, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Thanks for Blood Meridian cover. Working on checklist of Leonard and Virginia Woolf's Hogarth Press.
  - McCarthy to Woolmer. Als, 2 pages, February 25, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 6)